Atlas Shrugged, Ayn Rand's timeless classic,
tell us about how the world's best producers innovators and creative minds
disappear from a society crumbling under the weight of government intervention and collectivism.
But at its heart, it's a powerful philosophical declaration of individualism,
rational self-interest and the role of reason in human life.
In my life, Atlas Shrugged has inspired me to be great.
When I entered college I became frustrated by the irrationality around me.
I soon found philosophy appealing because of its respect for a reason and truth.
So I majored in it.
But ironically, it was in this field that I encountered some of reason's harshest critics.
After discussing this with my older brother, he introduced me to Atlas Shrugged and the works of Ayn Rand.
I was completely blown away by the powerful ideas.
I decided to use reason as the foundation for my life.
And a rational self-regarding happiness as my moral purpose.
With this new found clarity of vision, I ignored the irrational negative forces around me, and freed my mind from illogical limitations.
My life blossomed as I shifted my focus from parties and mindless activities to the pursuit of wisdom, art and filmmaking.
I graduated as a senior who showed the most academic improvement;
Found the courage to pursue the girl of my dreams;
And have embarked on my goal to create a major production company.
Just as this book helped me at a critical time in my life,
our society needs this books principles now more than ever.
We've recently witnessed the crumbling of our economic system.
And just as in Atlas Shrugged, politicians have wrongly blamed free market capitalism.
And have demonised innovators and producers.
Instead of preserving the individual rights of our country's citizens, the government have trampled them.
Hard working people are being looted through taxes, bailouts, stimulus bills and dollar devaluation policies.
instead of allowing free market system to work,
government leaders have rewarded irresponsible corporations who have the Washington connections.
While offering collective "solutions" that crushed the profit motive of producers, innovators and entrepreneurs,
by confiscating the fruits of their labor.
The Heroes of Atlas Shrugged simply wanted freedom.
Will we awake into the lessons of Atlas Shrugged?
Or will we find ourselves asking "who is John Galt?"