Simon's new at the factory.
If you ask him
he'll tell you it's a lousy job.
He has to sweep up and carry things around.
He only earns three dollars an hour.
Even so
Simon prefers working here
to the alternatives he sees for himself right now.
Although his wage is low
Simon appreciates the independence it gives him.
Next week he'll learn how to use a forming machine.
That will makes things more interesting.
That's Edgar,
the owner of the factory.
the only thing he really cares about is making profit.
Edgar would prefer to pay his workers a tiny fraction of their current wages
to keep more money for himself.
but he knows that wouldn't work.
Edgar is in competition with many other business owners.
They all need a steady supply of human labour.
When deciding whether or not to trade with an employer
workers consider wages but also working conditions and other benefits.
If Edgar's offers aren't attractive enough
workers won't sell him the labour he needs to run his factory.
So reluctantly Edgar ends up paying market prices for the labour
he buys.
In another part of town there's a celebration.
This group of concerned citizens just got a minimum wage law passed.
They were appalled
that miserly employers like Edgar
could get away with paying so little to workers like Simon.
The new minimum wage
is nine dollars an hour.
Unfortunately
this doesn't mean that everyone in the town will now
earn nine dollars or more.
We already saw
how the existence of competing buyers of labour influences the lower limit
on what Edgar can get away with paying his workers.
The upper limit on what Edgar will pay any worker
is the amount of extra revenue
he expects that worker's labour
will create for him
in a given period.
In other words
employers won't knowingly pay workers more than the extra income they generate.
They'd be losing money if they did that.
So what does the introduction of the minimum wage law mean for the
workers at Edgar's factory?
Vicky's work
generates twenty three dollars an hour for Edgar. And her wage is fifteen
dollars an hour.
For every hour that Vicky works for Edgar
he's left with an extra eight dollars
after he's paid her wage.
Because Vicky's wage is higher than nine dollars an hour
the new law doesn't affect her directly.
Bob's labor at the factory generates ten dollars an hour for Edgar,
and his wage is eight dollars an hour.
After paying Bob's wage Edgar is left with an extra two dollars
for every hour that Bob has worked.
But because Bob's wage
is less than the legal minimum,
if Edgar wants to keep him on
he'll have to pay him more.
Edgar calculates
that if he raises Bob's wage
to the new minimum of nine dollars he'll still be gaining one extra dollar for
every hour of Bob's labor, after his wages have been paid.
Although Edgar will profit less from employing Bob at nine dollars instead of eight,
a little profit is better than none.
So Bob gets a raise.
But the new law
is bad news for Simon.
Simon's labour generates only four dollars an hour for Edgar.
The nine dollar minimum wage
is five dollars more than that.
Edgar would be losing five dollars an hour
by keeping Simon on
at the new legal minimum.
So Simon doesn't get a raise.
Instead
he loses his job.
Edgar is irritated.
The minimum wage means
that if he wants to stay in business
he has to either invest in machines
to do the work that unskilled labourers like Simon were doing.
Or he has to move production to another country
where minimum wage laws aren't a problem.
Edgar believes
both of these options are less profitable for him
than employing local workers,
otherwise he wouldn't have hired Simon.
For Simon
the outlook is bleak.
Losing his job would have been bad enough,
but the minimum wage continues to disadvantage him even while he's
unemployed.
Because he's young
and doesn't have much experience, it's likely that the extra revenue Simon's
labour would create for any employer would be low.
Potential employers expect to lose money
hiring Simon
at the minimum wage
so they turn down his applications.
Simon was glad of his factory job, even with its low wage.
He hoped to build up experience
which would raise his productivity
and give him a chance to move to better paid and more satisfying work.
But the new law prevents him from doing so.
This is why the minimum wage has been described as removing the bottom rungs
from the economic ladder.
When we see social interactions that seem unfair
one response is to demand that the behaviour we disapprove of
be outlawed.
But we should keep in mind that this kind of intervention
has unintended consequences.
Some people suspect that prohibiting voluntary exchange often does more harm
than good.
They believe
the proper function of law
is to discourage the initiation of force,
and that we shouldn't create barriers that
prevent people from doing their best to peacefully improve their lives.
Do a web search for some of these terms if you're interested in learning more.